<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>de Lima, G. G.</title>
    <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on de Lima, G. G.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ggoetten.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Natural Fibre-Reinforced Polymer Composites: Manufacturing and Biomedical Applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tielidy-chapter2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tielidy-chapter2021/</guid>
      <description>Currently, the use of natural fibres as a reinforcement in composites presents many attractive benefits, including the reduction of materials from non-renewable sources and reduction of environmental impact. Intensive research is being carried out to develop biocomposites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Termodinâmica dos materiais</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/teaching/termo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/teaching/termo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post-graduate level on Thermodynamics of materials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of different drying methods on the chemical, nutritional and colour of yerba mate (Ilex paraguariensis) leaves</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/yerbamw2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/yerbamw2021/</guid>
      <description>This work investigates the effect of differentdrying processes on chemical, nutritional and leavescolour characteristics forIlex paraguariensisleaves. Theseprocesses were composed of typical drying techniques(roasting+rotary dryer and roasting+conveyor dryer), andcutting-edge techniques (microwave oven [MW], freeze-drying (FD) and oven dryer [OD]). The MW can be analternative technique, this is because the content ofphenolic compounds (77 mg/g), antioxidant capacity(DPPH and ABTS) (∼370 and∼1040μM TE/g), methylxan-thines and caffeoylquinic acids (2–4 mg/g) were similar,and sometimes higher, to the conventional drying pro-cesses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microfibrillated cellulose films containing chitosan and tannic acid for wound healing applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tameysam2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tameysam2021/</guid>
      <description>The effectiveness of tannic acid as antimicrobial and wound healing for burns have been shown for a century; however, uncontrolled target dosage may result in undesirable side-effects. Remarkably, tannic acid polyphenols compounds crosslinked with polymeric materials produce a strong composite containing the beneficial properties of this tannin. However, investigation of the crosslink structure and its antibacterial and regenerative properties are still unknown when using nanocellulose by mechanical defibrillation; additionally, due to the potential crosslink structure with chitosan, its structure can be complex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yerba Mate Extract in Microfibrillated Cellulose and Corn Starch Films as a Potential Wound Healing Bandage</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/yerba2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/yerba2020/</guid>
      <description>Microfibrillated cellulose films have been gathering considerable attention due to their high mechanical properties and cheap cost. Additionally, it is possible to include compounds within the fibrillated structure in order to confer desirable properties. Ilex paraguariensis A. St.-Hil, yerba mate leaf extract has been reported to possess a high quantity of caffeoylquinic acids that may be beneficial for other applications instead of its conventional use as a hot beverage. Therefore, we investigate the effect of blending yerba mate extract during and after defibrillation of Eucalyptus sp.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of alginate beads with encapsulated jabuticaba peel and propolis extracts to achieve a new natural colorant antioxidant additive</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/alginate2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/alginate2020/</guid>
      <description>This work aims to encapsulate anthocyanins and phenolic compounds extracted from a native Brazilian fruit peel - jabuticaba (Plinia cauliflora (Mart.) Kausel) and propolis from Tubuna (Scaptotrigona bipunctata) stingless bees, with great potential benefits for human health. The alginate encapsulation was conducted by the ionotropic gelation through the dripping into the CaCl2 solution. Both raw extracts were characterized by TPC - total phenolic content (Folin-Ciocalteu), AA -antioxidant activity (DPPH and ABTS assays), and TMAC - total monomeric anthocyanin concentration (pH differential method); as well as their resultant mixture (2:1 jabuticaba/propolis).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antioxidant, antibacterial and antitumoural activities of kraft lignin from hardwood fractionated by acid precipitation</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/kraftlignin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/kraftlignin/</guid>
      <description>Kraft lignin, so far useful for energy generation, has been gathering considerable attention as an alternative material to replace fossil-based resources mainly due to its high phenolic content. However, the wide molecular weight distribution and chemical composition heterogeneity led to the development of fractionation methods. Herein, to narrow such characteristics we used eucalypt kraft lignin fractionated at pH&amp;rsquo;s 9, 7, 5 and 3 by sequential acid precipitation. These lignin fractions were first characterised by simultaneous pyrolysis and trimethylsilylation (SPyT) with N-Methyl-N-(trimethylsilyl) trifluoroacetamide with posterior tests of antioxidant, antibacterial, and antitumour activities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enzymatic activities and analysis of a mycelium-based composite formation using peach palm (Bactris gasipaes) residues on Lentinula edodes</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/mycelium2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/mycelium2020/</guid>
      <description>By seeding fungus on top of industry residues, a mycelium can grow and form a compact network structure; however, it may not develop due to lack of optimal nutrients from the substrate. Consequently, peach-palm residues can be a potential alternative; so, to test this hypothesis, this work evaluates the effect of peach-palm residues as substrate for the growth of mycelium based on Lentinula edodes. They were also supplemented with cassava bran and various sources of nitrogen-ammonium sulphate, potassium nitrate, and soy flour—to analyse its effects on its physico-chemical, enzymatic activities, and thermal and mechanical properties of the final composite at 12 and 20 days of cultivation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tópicos Especiais em Engenharia e Ciência dos Materiais III – Físico química das superfícies</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/teaching/physico-chemistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/teaching/physico-chemistry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post-graduate level on Physical chemistry of surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Produção de farinha de pinhão funcional com compostos bioativos</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/pinhaoct/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/pinhaoct/</guid>
      <description>A araucária (Araucaria angustifolia (Bert.) O. Ktze) pertence à família Araucariaceae, e é uma das únicas espécies de coníferas nativas brasileiras com importância econômica (Zandavalli et al., 2004). A espécie tem sido explorada há mais de cem anos por sua qualidade de madeira, sendo usada nas indústrias de móveis e na construção civil. No entanto, a exploração predatória a incluiu na lista de espécies ameaçadas de extinção (Thomas, 2020) e sob proteção ambiental (Danner et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of cellulose size-concentration on the structure of polyvinyl alcohol hydrogels</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ftcel-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ftcel-2020/</guid>
      <description>Microfibrillated cellulose as a reinforcement agent has been investigated extensively due to their unique characteristics, which can reorder the structure of polymers and hydrogels leading to improved mechanical properties with minimal disadvantages in terms of the targeted original applications. However, effect of using a macro- to a micro-fibrillated cellulose onto polyvinyl alcohol hydrogels is still unknown, because of the unique ability for both to be produced as hydrogels from freeze-thawing mechanisms – hydrogen bonding - there is a potential synergism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Injectable bone substitute based on chitosan with polyethylene glycol polymeric solution and biphasic calcium phosphate microspheres</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/injectable-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/injectable-2020/</guid>
      <description>We described a method to produce an injectable bone substitute consisting of a solid and liquid phase, this solid was formed using the coacervation method consisting of a mixture of Hydroxyapatite (HAp) and beta-Tricalcium Phosphate (β-TCP) which the sodium alginate - precursor - was removed during sinterization. The biphasic calcium phosphate microspheres had varying size distributions depending on the flow rate and these microspheres were mixed with a polymeric solution, chitosan and polyethylene glycol, and depending on the ratio of these phases, the injectability results varied.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nanosuspension of pinhão seed coat development for a new high‐functional cereal bar</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/pinhaobarrinha-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/pinhaobarrinha-2020/</guid>
      <description>The seeds from Araucaria angustifolia —commonly named as pinhão—are important culturally, and viable regional food from Brazil. Although now considered an endangered species, methods to increase the awareness of this tree have been called upon attention. In light upon increasing such awareness, we utilized the seed coats of pinhão, which is considered a residue and discarded, in the development of cereal bars. Although the raw seed coats have a very high astringent flavor and impair the sensory taste; if considered as a nanoformulation, this strong astringent flavor is masked.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of unidirectional freezing using a thermal camera on polyvinyl (alcohol) for aligned porous cryogels</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/uni-free-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/uni-free-2020/</guid>
      <description>Unidirectional freeze casting for polymers and ceramics has been performed extensively; however, the mechanisms involved in unidirectional freezing are not thoroughly understood and therefore, in this study, polyvinyl (alcohol) hydrogels were freeze-thawed by unidirectional freezing and the resultant freezing profile was investigated using thermal imagery to comprehend the physical mechanism involved in the production of these aligned cryogels. The approach used follows a slight variation from what is currently used in literature, by enclosing the mould with insulating materials and leaving one side with a metal encasing for a fast freezing flow from the direction of the desired aligned of the structure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evaluation of the potential ecotoxicity of pyroligneous acid obtained from fast pyrolysis</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/biooil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/biooil/</guid>
      <description>Pyroligneous acid (PA) is a by-product of bio-oil, which is obtained by pyrolysis of the wood. This product has been tested for use in several areas, such as agriculture, as a promising green herbicide; however, there are few scientific data regarding its environmental impacts. For this study, an ecotoxicity testing battery, composed of Daphnia magna acute toxicity test, Allium cepa test and in vitro Comet assay with the rainbow trout gonad-2 cell fish line (RTG-2) were used to evaluate the acute toxicity and genotoxicity of PA obtained from fast pyrolysis of eucalyptus wood fines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis and in vivo evaluation of a scaffold containing wollastonite/β-TCP for bone repair in a rabbit tibial defect model</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ceramic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ceramic/</guid>
      <description>Scaffolds are models designed to aid the interaction between cells and extracellular bone matrix, providing structural support for newly formed bone tissue. In this work, wollastonite with β-tcp porous ceramic scaffolds were developed by the polymer sponge replication. Their microstructure, cell viability and bioactivity were tested. In vivo was performed to evaluate the use of a calcium silicate-based implant in the repair of rabbit tibias. Holes were made in the both proximal and distal tibial metaphysis of each animal and filled with calcium silicate-based implant, and in the left tibia, no implant were used, serving as control group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tough and novel dual-response PAA/P(NiPAAM-co-PEGDMA) IPN hydrogels with ceramics by photopolymerization for consolidation of bone fragments following fracture</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ipnhydrogel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ipnhydrogel/</guid>
      <description>In this work, a novel dual-response hydrogel for enhanced bone repair following multiple fractures was investigated. The conventional treatment of multiple bone fracture consists on removing smaller bone fragments from the body in a surgery, followed by the fixation of the bone using screws and plates. This work proposes an alternative for this treatment via in situ UV-initiated radical polymerization of a novel IPN hydrogel composed of PAA/P(NiPAAM-co-PEGDMA) incorporated with ceramic additives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The production of a novel poly(vinyl alcohol) hydrogel cryogenic spheres for immediate release using a droplet system</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/spheres/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/spheres/</guid>
      <description>Although freeze-thaw mechanism for producing crosslinked hydrogels is relatively easy and simple, it lacks sufficient integrity and support leading to modifications on its three-dimensional polymeric network arrangement during water removal—drying. Therefore, a strengthening method for obtaining cryogenic spheres of polyvinyl alcohol hydrogels is purposed by dispensing it as liquid droplets into a low temperature solution followed by a modification on its freeze-thaw cycles to confer a good geometry without aggregation. Various materials were incorporated into this hydrogel structure, including poly(acrylic acid) to impart pH sensitivity; hydroxyapatite to improve biocompatibility; and ciprofloxacin as an antimicrobial agent relevant for the treatment of osteomyelitis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prediction of yerba mate caffeine content using near infrared spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/yerba-mate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/yerba-mate/</guid>
      <description>There is a commercial and beneficial interest of producing yerba mate leaves into different grades of caffeine. This work uses a handheld and bench near-infrared (NIR) spectroscopy to compare and predict, using partial least squares (PLS) regression, the amount of caffeine in yerba mate leaves. Standards of pure caffeine were compared, using high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), with extracts of yerba mate. The bench spectroscopy gave a strong confidence model of caffeine prediction, whereas the handheld related to a fair model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tribo-mechanical properties and cellular viability of electrochemically treated Ti-10Nb and Ti-20Nb alloys</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tribotinb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tribotinb/</guid>
      <description>A number of researches have been concerned about the development of β-type titanium alloys because they can present good biocompatibility, non-cytotoxicity, suitable mechanical and corrosion resistance behavior. However, due to their chemical inertness property, the surfaces of the novel Ti alloys must be modified by different methods to improve their bioactivity. This work is focused on the electrochemical surface modification of Ti-10Nb and Ti-20Nb alloys by Plasma Electrolytic Oxidation (PEO) method in 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tópicos Especiais em Engenharia e Ciência dos Materiais III – Biomaterials</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/teaching/biomaterials/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +1100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/teaching/biomaterials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post-graduate level on biomaterials and the current materials used and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PEEK Physical Surface Modification: Evaluation Of Particles Leaching Process</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/peek/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/peek/</guid>
      <description>Polyetheretherketone (PEEK) has been prominent in orthopedic implants; however, it is inert, preventing interaction between the implant and adjacent bone tissues. One way to overcome this characteristic is physical modification its on surface by particle leaching promoting greater osseointegration. The objective of this research was to develop and characterize the PEEK using a surface modification technique via particle leaching. For of the samples, a layer deposition of NaCl was used on PEEK.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electrospun hydrogels composites for bone tissue engineering</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/electrospun/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/electrospun/</guid>
      <description>Electrospinning is one of the foremost nanotechnology applications to fabricate bone tissue engineering scaffolds with sizes in the nanometre range. It is regarded as a versatile, inexpensive and relatively simple methodology with potential for mimicking the nano- architecture of bones. In this chapter, the fabrication of three types of nanocomposites based on the biocompatible electrospun hydrogels, namely:(i) electrospun nanofibre-reinforced hydrogels, (ii) electrospun hydrogels with biological electrospray cells and (iii) electrospun hydrogels with antimicrobial activity, exclusively for the field of bone tissue regeneration are presented.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tailoring surface properties from nanotubes and anodic layers of titanium for biomedical applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tailoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tailoring/</guid>
      <description>The following chapter gives an overview on the anodic layers and nanotubes produced with plasma electrolytic oxidation. An introduction into the mechanisms involved in producing these nanofilms, such as the required processing parameters including voltage, current and time are discussed. In addition to an examination into the relation and the requirements for a good interface between the implant using these nanofilms and the bone, we also investigate and discuss the available commercial implants employing nanofilms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of the effects of orientation on freeze/thawed Polyvinyl alcohol hydrogel properties</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/orientationft/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/orientationft/</guid>
      <description>Although hydrogels produced via freeze-thawing (F/T) technique have been thoroughly studied in literature, stretching hydrogels in between freeze-thawing cycles could change its properties and might be modulated for drug delivery systems. The PVA hydrogels and Caffeine-contained PVA hydrogels were created by freezing for 20 minutes using liquid nitrogen and 4 hours thawing at 4 °C. The results revealed that the PVA/CAF hydrogel with two F/T cycles followed by two stretching (S) cycles delivered the best response.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electrospinning of hydrogels for biomedical applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/electrospinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/electrospinning/</guid>
      <description>The field of biomedical applications for hydrogels requires the development of nanostructures with specific controlled diameter and mechanical properties. Nanofibers are ideal candidates for these advanced requirements, and one of the easiest techniques that can produce one-dimensional nanostructured materials in fibrous form is the electrospinning process. This technique provides extremely thin fibers with controlled diameter and highly porous microstructure with interconnected pores. Electrospinning demonstrates extreme versatility allowing the use of different polymers for tailoring properties and applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Composite cryogels for dual drug delivery and enhanced mechanical properties</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/compositecryogels2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/compositecryogels2018/</guid>
      <description>In this study, we present a simple and effective process that integrates hydrogels with drugs + ceramics via physical crosslinks resulting in improved mechanical properties. These cryogels have the potential for controlled drug release and stimulus responsive behavior. The hydrogels were produced from polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) and polyacrylic acid by varying the molecular weight of the polymers, via freeze‐thawing technique. The cryogels were combined with two ceramics: (1) a combination of beta‐tricalcium phosphate, wollastonite, magnesium silicate and (2) titanium dioxide nanopowder.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis and in Vivo Behavior of PVP/CMC/Agar Hydrogel Membranes Impregnated with Silver Nanoparticles for Wound Healing Applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/synthinvivo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/synthinvivo/</guid>
      <description>The field of wound healing has seen an increase in research activity in wound care and hydrogel-based dressings have been targeted as a solution for these applications. Hydrogels with silver nanoparticles can present many advantages for this field. However, if the aggregation and sterilization of this product have not been carefully considered, the effectiveness or use could be limited. Therefore, in the current study, a hydrogel-based wound dressing membrane was developed using polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP), polyethylene glycol (PEG), agar, and carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Platelet-Rich Plasma, Hydroxyapatite, and Chitosan in the Bone and Cartilaginous Regeneration of Femoral Trochlea in Rabbits: Clinical, Radiographic, and Histomorphometric Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/bonechitosan2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/bonechitosan2018/</guid>
      <description>The aim of this study was to evaluate the trochlear bone and cartilaginous regeneration of rabbits using the association of PRP, chitosan, and hydroxyapatite. Hole was made in rabbit troches, one hole in each animal remained empty (group C), and one was filled by a combination of PRP, chitosan, and hydroxyapatite (group T). Clinical-orthopedic, radiographic, and histomorphometric evaluations were performed. Clinical-orthopedic evaluation showed lameness of two members of the T group and one member of group C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure Response for Cellulose-Based Hydrogels Via Characterization Techniques</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/structurecellulose/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/structurecellulose/</guid>
      <description>Hydrogels are three-dimensional cross-linked polymeric networks capable of imbibing substantial amounts of water or biological fluids and are widely used in biomedical applications, especially in pharmaceutical industry as drug delivery systems. Although their solvent content can be over 99%, hydrogels still retain the appearance and properties of solid materials, and the structural response can include a smart response to environmental stimuli (pH, temp, ionic strength, electric field, presence of enzyme, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Healing of the reto-abdominal musculature in rabbits submitted to laparorrhaphy with suture threads based of chitosan, catgut and polyglactin 910 (In portuguese)</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/healingsuture/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/healingsuture/</guid>
      <description>Objetivou-se com este estudo avaliar o processo de cicatrização da musculatura reto-abdominal em coelhos submetidos à laparotomia e laparorrafia utilizando-se o fio de sutura à base de quitosana, comparando-o aos fios de categute cromado e poliglactina 910. Foram utilizados 24 coelhos adultos, divididos aleatoriamente em quatro grupos: quitosana e categute 15 dias (QC-15dias), quitosana e categute 30 dias (QC-30 dias), quitosana e poliglactina 910 15 dias (QP-15 dias) e quitosana e poliglactina 910 30 dias (QP-30 dias).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controlled Release of Poorly Soluble Active Ingredients from Bioresorbable Polymers</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/controlledrelease/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/controlledrelease/</guid>
      <description>With increasing technologies for drug development, the demand to improve bioavailability of poorly-water soluble drugs have been gathered many interest. The low bioavailability and toxicity with these drugs focused the research to develop different strategies to counter its effects. In this chapter, we will aim to look at the problems on the different formulations and delivery routes with poorly water soluble drugs. In addition, we introduce solutions to overcome the problems of poorly-water soluble drugs by describing the influence of biodegradable hydrogels; the technology development and treatment, which has led to innovations in the field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of anodizing time on the mechanical properties of porous titania coatings formed by micro-arc oxidation</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/maomecprop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/maomecprop/</guid>
      <description>Porous TiO2 coatings were produced on commercially pure Ti substrates by micro-arc oxidation (MAO) in 1.0M H2SO4 electrolyte for different anodizing times. Their mechanical properties were assessed by means of instrumented indentation, XRD residual stress measurements and scratch resistance tests. The rutile/anatase ratio increased from ~0 up to 84% in the 10–360s anodizing time range, with further increase of coating thickness, porosity and roughness. Titania coatings produced for 180 and 360s had poor adhesion and uneven surfaces with spontaneous detachment from the substrate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical properties of anodic titanium films containing ions of Ca and P submitted to heat and hydrothermal treatment</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ttaomctio2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ttaomctio2/</guid>
      <description>Anodic oxidation is a technique widely used to improve the bioactivity of Ti surface. In this study, micro-arc oxidation (MAO) was used to obtain an anodic film incorporating Ca and P ions to evaluate the effect of heat and hydrothermal treatment on the mechanical and in vitro bioactivity properties of these new layers. The MAO process was carried out using (CH3COO)2Ca·H2O and NaH2PO4·2H2O electrolytes under galvanostatic mode (150mA/cm2). The thermal treatments were made at 400°C and 600°C in air atmosphere while hydrothermal treatment was made in an alkaline water solution at 130°C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bioactive composites fabricated by freezing‐thawing method for bone regeneration applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/bioactiveft2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/bioactiveft2016/</guid>
      <description>Hydrogels are widely used for controlled delivery of therapeutic agents. However, hydrogels lack bioactivity to encourage bone formation and mechanical integrity. Moreover, chemically crosslinked hydrogels exhibit cytotoxic effect. To overcome these limitations poly-vinyl alcohol (PVA) and poly-acrylic acid (PAA) blends were combined with ceramic materials based on ? tricalcium phosphate, wollastonite, and magnesium silicate with different pore size distributions. The final 3D matrix was physically crosslinked using various freeze thawing (F/T) cycles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extraction Method Plays Critical Role in Antibacterial Activity of Propolis-Loaded Hydrogels</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/propolishydrogels2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/propolishydrogels2016/</guid>
      <description>Extracted propolis has been used for a long time as a remedy. However, if the release rate of propolis is not controlled, the efficacy is reduced. To overcome this issue, extracted propolis was added to a cryogel system. Propolis collected from southern Brazil was extracted using different methods and loaded at different concentrations into polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) and polyacrylic acid hydrogels as carrier systems. The material properties were investigated with a focus on the propolis release profiles and the cryogel antibacterial properties against 4 different bacteria, namely: Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli, Salmonella typhimurium, and Pseudomonas putida.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A novel pH-sensitive ceramic-hydrogel for biomedical applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/novelph/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/novelph/</guid>
      <description>Innovations on the field of smart hydrogels are now being held with loads of advantages. With recent progress, smart polymers can now be used on the market for specific target/objectives desired on medicine. However, the field of smart hydrogels has not been fully overviewed on the ground for drug delivery. In this study, a novel pH-sensitive smart hydrogel for drug delivery was investigated. Polyvinyl-alcohol (PVA) with polyacrylic acid (PAA) was blended adding synthetic hydroxyapatite (Hap) with freeze-thawed cycles and its effects were studied in terms of mechanical strength, bioactivity, and drug release profile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart Hydrogels: Therapeutic Advancements in Hydrogel Technology for Smart Drug Delivery Applications</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/smarthydrogels/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/smarthydrogels/</guid>
      <description>Hydrogels are three-dimensional cross-linked polymeric networks capable of imbibing substantial amounts of water or biological fluids and are widely used in biomedical applications, especially in pharmaceutical industry as drug delivery systems. Although their solvent content can be over 99%, hydrogels still retain the appearance and properties of solid materials, and the structural response can include a smart response to environmental stimuli (pH, temp, ionic strength, electric field, presence of enzyme, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparation and Characterization of Novel Poly(Vinyl Alcohol) (PVA) and  Poly(Acrylic  Acid)  (PAA)  Hydrogels  for  Sensitive Hydrogels </title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/preparation/</guid>
      <description>Stimuli Sensitive hydrogels have enormous potential in various applications. Various environmental variables are found in the body, such as low pH and elevated temperatures. For this reason, either pH-sensitive and/or temperature-sensitive hydrogels can be used for site-specific controlled drug delivery. For many applications hydrogels require a very rapid time-response in terms of their sensitivity to either pH and/or temperature. Rapid time-responsive sensitivity is a research field which is still in development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improved tribo-mechanical behavior of CaP-containing TiO2 layers produced on titanium by shot blasting and micro-arc oxidation</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ticapshot2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ticapshot2014/</guid>
      <description>The combination of shot blasting (SB) and micro-arc oxidation (or anodic oxidation&amp;mdash;AO) in titanium surfaces was shown to provide enhanced conditions for cell differentiation and osseointegration than those provided by SB or AO alone. This study associated both methods aiming to attain titania layers on Ti with adequate tribo-mechanical features for bone implants. SB was performed using alumina particles, and titania layers were grown by AO using a CaP-based electrolyte. Mechanical properties and scratch resistance were characterized at nanoscale by instrumented indentation and nanoscratch, and correlated with morphological and microstructural changes (XRD, SEM, EDS, AFM, and profilometry).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical properties of bioactive Ti obtained by anodic oxidation with subsequent thermal treatment using solutions based on Ca / P (In portuguese)</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/mechproppt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/mechproppt/</guid>
      <description>O objetivo deste trabalho é modificar a superfície de titânio obtido por oxidação anódica com eletrólitos contendo Ca/P e posterior tratamento térmico, a fim de evitar fragilidade e melhorar as propriedades mecânicas nestas camadas anódicas. O material utilizado neste trabalho foi titânio comercialmente puro (grau 2). As amostras foram polidas usando lixas de SiC granulometria $600, e depois anodizadas em modo galvanostático em temperatura ambiente em uma solução eletrolítica contendo 0,14 mol/l acetato de cálcio monohidratado ((CH3COO)2CA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nanomechanical properties of bioactive films grown on low energy ion implanted Ti</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ti-nano/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/ti-nano/</guid>
      <description>Surface modification processes such as the alkali-heat treatment (AHT) can be employed in order to improve the titanium osseointegration with living tissues. Sodium titanate films produced by AHT presented high in vitro bioactivity when soaked in simulated body fluid. In order to produce bioactive surfaces and also improve the tribo-mechanical response of AHT films grown on Ti, samples were submitted to H, N and O low energy ion implantation (glow discharge—GD) at different working conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tribo-mechanical characterization of rough, porous and bioactive Ti anodic layers</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tribotio2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/tribotio2/</guid>
      <description>Rough and porous titanium oxide layers, which are important features for improving the osseointegration of Ti implants with bone tissues, are obtained through the technique of anodic oxidation. The thicknesses of such coatings are typically in the order of micrometers, and their mechanical characterization can be assessed by instrumented indentation, provided that the composite nature of the surface is considered. Titania anodic layers were produced on Ti under galvanostatic mode using Ca–P-based electrolytes (a mixture of (CH3COO)2Ca⋅H2O and NaH2PO4⋅2H2O), employing current densities (J) of 150 mA/cm2 and 300 mA/cm2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elastic modulus and hardness of bioactive Ti obtained by anodic oxidation using Ca/P-based solutions</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/elasticcap2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/publications/elasticcap2009/</guid>
      <description>Anodic oxidation is a promising technique to become titanium surfaces bioactive, by simultaneously changing the surface morphology, structure and chemical properties. Calcium and phosphorus based electrolytes were used to produce anodic films on c.p. Ti with two different current densities, 150 mA/cm2 and 300 mA/cm2. Morphology and structure were examined by SEM, EDS and XRD, and elastic modulus and hardness of the surfaces by instrumented indentation. Besides rutile and anatase TiO2 phases, hydroxyapatite was also identified on the films, as well as the segregation of very soft Ca and P-rich zones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>403</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/403/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/403/</guid>
      <description> Sorry, you don&#39;t have permission to do that </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>404</title>
      <link>https://ggoetten.github.io/404/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ggoetten.github.io/404/</guid>
      <description>404: File not found Sorry, that doesn&#39;t seem to be here   This photo was actually on my Ph.D. presentation to demonstrate how hard it was to write a paper with some results I found.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
